Noel Phyllis Birkby Papers, 1932-1994
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Opens w/CU of women's faces. "Adelante Las Hermanas En La Lucha," then there's a French sign - "You Are Welcome" then in English "Lesbian and Straight Together"; beautiful, hand-drawn graphics. Sisters Unite, hand drawn sign. Another hand drawn sign: Our Hands, Feet, Bodies, Minds Are Tools For Change. Architectural details of the loft, it looks like they're in a loft. Fifth St. may have been an old women's center? Meeting - Welfare Mothers At Noon - another sign. Women's Building - another sign; Women's Interart Center; Gay Pride sign; Food Co-op; This Building Is Ours. The Price? Our Commitment (Jane O'Wyatt told me about this - take over of the Fifth St. building) Sign says "We Shall Not Be Moved." "Lesbians Unite" "Health Care" signs. Early comic drawing "Keep On Trucking, Sisters" "Never Underestimate The Power Of A Woman" another sign beautifully done, good contrast, B&W. Babytalk Magazine, dated material. Old falling apart interior structure of loft, interesting looking. "Our Small Group Is Fixing This Room To Be Used By All Sisters As A Lounge - Donations Accepted" hand drawn sign. Dark footage. Great shot of women's gathering in the space. Medium shots of some of the women, soft focus, didn't have enough light. Sharp focus of a woman in crochet hat, Buffy Johnson, the painter? Great shot of whoever it is. Women singing or performing, girl child, aluminum paper background. This is a good film. Children holding on to parents' hands - nice shot. Long shot of the group holding hands in a circle. Nicely lit and good exposure. Older woman, 60s or 70s, looks like a skit is being performed.
121. "FIRST 1/2 OF MARCH '71?. WOMEN'S MARCH '71?.
Well exposed, no scratches. Looks like historic women holding large banners in NY. "New York Radical Feminists" banner goes all the way across the street on sheets. "Lesbians For Nixon" woman w/big smile carrying sign, then waves. Shots of crowd and shots of back of woman wearing a motorcycle helmet. Interesting closeups of men who I don't know if they're marching or not. Another banner "Equality" - equals sign. CU of woman in dark glasses smiling. Beautiful shot of Frances Doughty and woman in CU, dark glasses, long hair. Another big banner "Brooklyn NOW" Women wearing the fist in the circle. Women's lib sign. Great shot with radical banner behind. Lots of reds and whites in the image. Policemen, newscasters. Sappho? Was A Woman banner. Good shots of people in the street. A sign saying "One to One Committee NOW". More newscaster. Abortion Is A Woman's Right sign. Historical woman photo. Huge comic book-like billboard sign on a building. Soft focus of march. Sign - Smash Sexism, Women's Libertion NOW t-shirt. Crush Phallic Imerialism - nice shot showing a lot of women holding sign. Kate Millett is in crowd w/Betty Friedan right after sign (maybe) soft focus, anyway, not great. Bystanders. Another banner "Lesbian (something)" Women marching by shoe shop - "Shoes For Women" Woman reading as she marches, may be changing. Kate Millet in red - soft focus. CU of other women. Back to Kate. Dog w/sign on it - can't read. CU woman's face - pull out to medium shot. Jan Oxenberg possibly w/purple blouse w/white trim? Street scene. Angela Davis sign - large B&W photo. Good shot of Kate w/arm around somebody [Linda Clarke?], w/historic woman photo in background and a woman of color, finally, next to her. CU of Louise Fishman w/short hair. Woman's hand holding pamphlet saying Woman's World. Shot of another woman, don't know who, several. Sign - "Gay Male Feminist" CU of another woman. Button - "Sister" Angry woman yelling, holding a banner, very dramatic, pretty good not scratched. Shot - "Sisterhood Is Powerful" sign. More banners. Back of Kate w/arms around someone from behind. "Lesbians Unite" in focus. GAA embrodiered on hip pocket of dungarees. A lot of women all together. "Women's Liberation Is A Lesbian Plot." Policemen walking in front of sign. Soft focus on police. Women's Lib sign seen through a bus. Woman marching alone down street w/gusto. Women straggling down the street w/"Plot" sign. Nice CU of holding hands, arms around each other. Two women in white shirts arms around each other. Kate Millett again, in red, w/blonde woman also in red. Men marching. Women in dresses marching. "Unity" banner. "Phallic Imperialism" sign of New York Radical Feminists. Crowd shot, really good, around "Lesbians Unite" sign. Lots of nice crowd shots now, very seventies, good exposure, good color. More of Kate w/girlfriend and a third woman, smiling at camera. Westchester Coalition sign. Quality Child Care Service For Working Mothers sign. Chick Is A Dirty Word handwritten sign. Woman w/hand over mouth. Now, microphones at space where rally will be. A woman at microphones. We Are With You - French women's liberation sign. Then, B&W - good shot of microphones in B&W and some of the speakers. African-American woman in crowd, CU. I think Ti-Grace Atkinson(?) CUs of people, African-American man, Euro-Am. women. March For Equality banner behind speakers, big camera. Huge rally, now, shot of thousands in crowd. Great crowd shots. Not scratched. Soft focus CU. Betty Friedan, soft focus. Dark footage at end.
122. GAY MARCH 7/71.
Jill Johnston. Louise Fishman. Slightly overexposed. Then, out of focus. Good exposure - woman waving under Burlington House. Site of march sign - We Are Everywhere. Two women holding hands, arms around each other. Slightly overexposed. CU of Kate Millett eating, overexposed. Two woman kissing, out of focus, overexposed. Women's Lib button. Lots of overexposure. Not useable. Then, shot I think of Kate from behind. Maybe Kate and Jill - two longhaired women w/arms around each other -don't know who. Two other women, laughing. Some good, some scratched. More over exposed. Gay love, God's love - overexposed sign.
122A. GAY MARCH, 1977. Approx. 3 min.
Woman with sign "Gay Pride '77." Woman with hands raised above head forming triangle shape with thumbs and pointer fingers. Marchers. Band of police officers in march. Marchers. "Lesbian Feminist Liberation" banner. "Lesbian Seperatists Love Women" banner. "Dykes Tykes" banner and float. Women marching. 3 women with cameras. 2 women--one could be Louise Fishman. Too fast to tell. Close-up of woman with dark curly hair. Placard with Anita Bryant's face in center of swastika. Marchers. "Dykes Tykes" float. "National Organization for Women" banner. Marchers.
122B. GAY MARCH, 1977. Approx. 3 min.
"Lesbian Feminist Liberation" banner. "Anita Bryant is garbage" placard. Woman sitting on ground. Seems to be post-march. Banners are hung on fence, placards on ground. Crowds of people sitting around talking in a park?
123. "IT'S ALL RIGHT TO BE WOMAN THEATER. Super 8, B&W
Poster - Change For My Sisters poster, title and woman's face illustration. Cuts to a woman. Looks like 1986. Dark. Some shots of women's faces. Much is too dark to use. Another poster - graphic illustration of a hand carrying a cup, then a little cage around a brick, a woman w/a scrub brush and foot, pregnant woman, a drawing shot in CU, no scratches, useable, looks like a gallery in the theatre w/various drawings hung on walls. Kind of gray but useable. Sojourner Truth poster, woman. Emma Goldman. Poster w/a lot of women's names, more drawings from the exhibition. Very good.
124. "IT'S ALL RIGHT TO BE WOMAN THEATER.
Soft focus of woman's face, slightly soft focus of another one. Looks like a women's theatre group. Some clear shots nicely lit of this group. Pull back to showing the group together sitting in a circle w/guitar. Nicely lit well exposed. CU of guitar is out of focus. A woman listening, in focus, well lit, several women. Action of one woman holding another while laughing and trying to pull away. Well lit and clear. Another woman yelling, a larger older woman, fairly okay. Another woman seems to be crying, close up of very dramatically gesturing hands. Two hands holding, again dramatic gestures, well lit and clear. Interaction between two women, their hands and a face. Nicely lit, interesting shot - a very good roll of women's theatre group. Women pointing at one another
125. "IT'S ALL RIGHT TO BE WOMAN THEATER/JJ TYPING.. Super 8, B&W
Dark, mostly; some shots of women's faces. A woman with a prop.
126. "IT'S ALL RIGHT TO BE WOMAN THEATER". Super 8, B&W
Drawing of a stick figure called "Me", big feet. All Right To Be Women Theatre. CU of Me, looks like a Phyllis Birkby self-portrait. My friends, stick figures holding hands "My Friends" Looks like title of show is The Popular Crowd. Drawing of a boy I had a crush on. He was in the Popular Crowd. The saga of my hairy legs or how my heart hurt. The boy is saying to the two girls, "Did you see her hairy legs?" Little stick figure drawings. "Did you see Sue's hairy legs?" Drawing of a heart w/lightning bolt through it. Line drawing of a lot of feet and shoes and a sign, "How My Mother Saved The Day, I Thought" "Can I shave my legs?" Bunch of hairy legs w/mother w/hairy legs and me w/hairy legs. My Fantasy. Ronson shaver plugged. THE END sign, then a woman walking through so you see these were on the wall. Women's Theatre - very good exposure. Back to realistic photography. In production, one sticks her tongue out, one w/mouth open. Beautifully lit and shot well. Good roll. One medium long shot showing a circle of women sitting together. Zoom up to a woman who is talking. Shows how group circle. Very well exposed sign of the play "A Chant For My Sisters." Shot of a ladder, woman listening. Best exposed of the theatre rolls.
127. "PATCHAPINES E-DAY/42nd STREET/PEACE DEMO". (color)
42nd Street: Night. Dark exposure. Close up of man's face, zoom out: standing in doorway. Close up of movie marquee. Head shot of woman with cigarette. Full shot of movie marquee. Close up of bottom edge of marquee, zoom in. Blinking marquee lights reflected in chrome. Woman lights cigarette. Med. shot of two men shaking hands. Zoom to close up of faces, zoom out. Splice. Shot of movie marquees. Close up of woman staring into camera. Zoom from long shot of couple standing to close up, zoom out. Medium shot of man with cigarette. Marquee. Close up of words on marquee, "Butch" & "Maggie". Side close up of man. Shot of car headlights moving past. Close up of red blinking taillight. Another. Daytime--American flag waving in the wind. Nighttime--close up of (cop car?) lights flashing, yellow and blue. Interior(?) extreme long shot of person on stage or other elevated surface. Exterior full-length shot of lighted window display w/female mannequin. Close up of glowing "Don't Walk" traffic sign. Med. shot of Hare Krishna couple dancing, zoom out. Same, from back. Close up of banner, zoom out, zoom back in.
Peace Demo: Long shot of barricade, two women climbing over it. Crowd shot: faces, woman with blonde bouffant. Close up of police officer. Crowd shot. Woman standing on barrier. Med. closeups of people's heads and shoulders as they walk by. Quick shots of people's faces. More crowd shots: people walking down stairs. Long shot two people on an elevated surface, red flag in back. Long shot of side of building, crowd. Long shot of people dancing on roof of entrance porch of large building. Zoom out. Man holding newspaper torch. Med. shot of man laughing in crowd. Extreme long shot of people dancing on roof, zoom in. Blue flash. Med. shot, zoom out of large paper skull hung from man's neck. Another shot of people on roof. Close up of back of news camera person's head, camera. Zoom out and pan down to reporter interviewing protestor, zoom in on her face. Long shot of crowd, banner above says "Pig Press...." Shot of red banner, says "Free Bobby." Man leaning against speakers. Crowd shot. Two red flags, crossed. Shot of protestors on roof. Long shot of banner. Individual close ups of men in uniforms. Military? Marchers walking toward camera. Med. shot of riot cop juxtaposed against street. Head shot of man shouting. Mounted policemen seen fr. below. Backlit. Med. long shot cops in riot gear lined up in front of street. Close up of bullhorn. Long shot of moon, framed betw. buildings.
128. WOMEN'S LIB. MARCH, A. 16mm
Looks like rephotography of Super 8 that she has on Women's Lib March. Looks like Kate Millett, Angela Davis. Small freezes on women's faces. Only optical printing that changes is a few short freezes of faces. Refer to Film #39. Blow up of Super 8.
129. "WOMEN'S LIBERATION MARCH TRIAL BLOWUPS.. 16mm.
130. WOMEN'S LIB 26 AUG 1970
131. WOMEN'S STRIKE FOR PEACE AND EQUALITY. 16mm Early '70s. [26 Aug 1970]
Roll of 7252 optically printed, 16 mm. color. Live action of a women's lib demonstration, TV news cameras, crowds, camera follows policeman doing crowd control. "No peace for a peace" - women's sign, "Male Chauvinists You Better Start Shaking." Women marching, news cameras set on high above the crowd. People giving peace sign from cafes to marchers. More TV news. People watching from windows. "Don't Iron While The Strike Is Hot" - Women's Strike August, Strike Headquarters 229 Lexington Ave. High School Feminism Is Alive and Growing. Power To The Women. Women's Strike For Peace and Equality. Women's fists in the air. Female Disc Jockey Wants Liberation And Job. Nicely exposed shot of the march in front of sign saying Fieldcrest. Nice overview of a long march. A freezeframe on a face - Rita Mae Brown? Equal Jobs sign. Playboy Club, Bunny flag flying. Freezeframe of the bunny flag. Good condition, not scratched at all.
132. UNTITLED
TRAVEL
133. "BAHAMAS". (color)
Shot of foamy water crashing on grainy beach, panning around. Again. Still water. Tiny fish swimming around in water. Close up of plant life in water. Close up tracking shot of small fish. Unexposed strip.
Med. shot of shells in water. Tracking shot (right to left) of waves rolling onto beach, to where a woman and a man are piling sand. Shot of man's legs, with water washing over his feet. Med. shot of man making sandcastle. Close up of limbs carving castle. Med. shot of the woman, man in foreground. More shots of castle building. Close ups of sandcastle towers. Close ups of finished sandcastle. Unexposed strip. Jump cuts between close ups of sandcastle and wide shot of ocean and dunes. Nice visual juxtaposition. Black strip of film.
Interior shot, dimly lit, of woman lying in bed under covers, being fed by man slightly offscreen. New angle of same. Close up of woman's face. Close up of woman's arm hanging over side of bed. Med. side shot of woman. Close up of her face. Exterior shot of two people on hill overlooking sea. Closer shot of same. Med. long shot of woman walking into camera. Med. long shot of man fishing. Med. shot of man w/fishing pole walking to camera. Long and medium shots of waves crashing on rocky shore. Unexposed strip. Med. shot of person fishing, zoom out and then in. Shot of ocean, person swims into frame. Med. shot of man standing in water. Close up of woman taking off her snorkling mask. Med. shot, from side, of man looking out of frame. Med. shot of woman bent over. Close up of man's face. Long shot of 5 people walking down street to docks where all the boats are, zoom out. Extra long shot of same, zoom in. Subjects wave to camera, dance around. Black strip of film.
Close up of man's face. Close up of woman's face. Wide shot of water, shoreline in distance, zoom out. Camera pans horizon. Long shot of horizon, edge of boat in bottom of frame.
134. "CANYON DE CHELLY. 8mm. Color.
Looks like shot in Utah or Canyonlands. I think she is referring to the architect, but the forms are all natural, not manmade. Beautiful red caves, red rocks, looks like poured cement, but poured by nature. Unscratched, good shape, good color, good focus. Canyon de Chelley, the White House, Indian ruins. Red water, very expansive filming. Series of four frames at a time, then one of them says "The End" on it but really isn't. Then an arrow going different ways. Then footprints that rangers make for tours. One little scratch goes through the film. Shot in true Birkby style. From dusk, night to morning, same location. Rest is all black.
135. "MARYLAND JULY 4TH. (color)
Close up of man's head. Close up of him squeezing a pimple? Red haired man reading, another man. Pan through the interior of house. Lots of windows, zoom in on chandelier. Long shot of boat sailing by on lake. Exterior shot of boathouse. Zoom out wide, to boats sailing past. Long shots of men urinating in garden. Head shot of redheaded man. Shot of abstract reflections in water, undulating on surface. Pretty. Two backlit shots through branches. More abstract light patterns in pool. Close up of corner of pool from overhead. Shot of more light abstractions in pool. Med. shot zoom to close up from inside house through windows of lake view. Backlit shot of trees swaying in wind. Close up of windowpanes: raining outside. close up of light fixture. Close up of top of chair back. Very dark shots of foxes in a pen. Exterior long shot of men on a lawn, pan to stately white house. Again. Jump cuts between med. shots of white flowers. Shot of facade of house. Med. shot of men on lawn with water in the background. Long shot of shoreline, pan across. Med. shot of men walking, from behind. Backlit leaves against sky. Long shots of gardens: a statue from three sides. Under the arbor. Jump cut to statue. Med. shot of flower. Head shot of other statue. Long shot of road going out of gardens. Long shot of statue, head shot from either side. Setting sun through tree branches.
136. "MARYLAND".
Horseback riding in Maryland. Well established white wood house on lawn. Man sitting in tree jumps from tree. Woman goofing off. Everyone is goofing off. Kid. Point of view driving a car. Beagle in the woods. Hiking in the woods. By the seashore w/dog. Beagle and two other dogs.
137. MISCELLANEOUS ROAD FOOTAGE A. Super 8 color. 7244 Looks like more trees at the beach, soft focus, blue haze. Street scene in some city. Capitol dome? Rocky River Ranch gates. Cute woman smiling and CU of her through a windshield, driving a truck. Next shot, nicely shot of woman w/baseball cap on that reads, "Smilers". Looks like a mixed sports team, baseball game, focus is soft except for those two CUs of the woman's face.
138. MISC. ROAD FOOTAGE B. Super 8 color. [1984, Los Angeles]
Looks like Olympic sports event. Swimming or diving, XXIII, Games of the 23rd Olympics Los Angeles. Focus is all soft. Except for the swimming lanes. Judges and swimming lanes and long shots are nice color is good and look like they've never been projected. Perfect. Overview of the street around the Olympics, w/palm trees, people on diving platforms.
139. MISC. ROAD FOOTAGE C - HIGHWAY.
Highway shot at different angles stretching off into sky. Film gave blue haze to everything. Turns camera upside down and to either side. Intermittent scratch later in the film. Landscape shot from car. Buttes, beautiful stormy sky at dusk, rainbow, no scratches. Ends up at Olympics at L.A.
140. MISC ROAD FOOTAGE D.
More highway - blurred of vegetation, buildings and building details, iron grill fence, soft focus. Parts are good focus, part soft.
141. MISC. ROAD FOOTAGE E.
Peacock. Ferris wheel. Some Fantasyland. Maybe Disneyland. Crowd scenes are soft focus. Children's playground is good. Louisiana journey - probably a boatride. Scandanavia, gondola entrance. Dark footage. Then daylight, soft focus. Inflated balloons, soft focus.
142. MISC. ROAD FOOTAGE F.
Same soft focus, details of a house w/horsedrawn carriage in front, saying Carriage Tours Savannah. Confederate flag. Looks like Savannah, w/southern homes, porches and wooden grillwork around the porches. Could be 1965, there is a 65 between the sprocket holes. Road, highway, then park - woman in bathing suit w/baseball cap walking toward camera, waving to Phyllis, big smile. (Might be Louise Fishman). Horse's head over a fence.
143. MISC ROAD FOOTAGE G.
Sunlight through the trees, intermittent scratch, same hazy, soft focus highway, water, street lamp by the beach, window frames of the beach. Motel, something Alvin's Island, either a motel or restaurant. More highway - road trip. Buildings, southern again, trees, southern mansion.
144. OLYMPICS OUT OF FOCUS FIELD HOCKEY. Sports stadium. [1984]
Out of focus game. Field hockey. Bad roll.
145. OLYMPICS I - OUTDOOR WOMEN'S SWIM MEET. [1984]
Outdoor women's swim and diving meet. Perfect shape. Shot with an eye for design. Full stadium - looks like L.A. Could be olympics. 23rd Olympics. refer to #104.
146. OLYMPICS II. [1984]
Track meets, flags, huge crowds, five rings. Focus not always good on CUs, good on long crowd shots. Colors are great. Wheelchair event, but focus is not good. Pretty good of men in yellow suits, a band, carrying instruments, walking on the track. Most out of focus.
147. OLYMPICS III. [1984]
Women in straw hat with pins on it w/track behind. Crowd scene. Track again, focus is good. Wheelchair, disabled, special olympics. Regular Olympic flag flying. Running - soft focus. Nice long shot of the stadium.
148. PATCHAPINES.(color)
Close up of man's face. Camera pans faces of people on porch, to extreme close up of hands. Patchapines sign. Close up of woman holding camera up to face. Jumps cuts between shots of flora, people. Jump cut to the beach. Long shot of a woman in the water. A woman gets up off the sand and moves to the water, a man goes with her. Ends in longshot. Med. long shot, parallel to shoreline, of waves rolling onto beach; truncated headless bodies of people pass by. Unexposed strip. Shot of people clustered together, lying on beach. Camera moves around them in a circle. They wave, are obviously enjoying themselves. Zoom in and out of the people, more circling of them as they perform synchronized movements with their legs and arms. Camera zooms in, then out as they disperse. More shots of rolling waves and truncated bodies walking past. Same, camera turned on side. Same, camera turned upside down, Same, camera turned on other side. Now camera right side up. Cycle repeats. Shots of rolling waves, kid playing in sand, truncated bodies walking past.
149. SAIGON.
Dark street scenes of Saigon. Too dark to use. Good exposure of man w/pink rickshaw, pedalling. Street scenes w/bicycles. People on bicycles. Second reel - all black.
150. SAIGON [?]. Approx. 3 min.
Many scenes of people, cars, bicycles, motocycles on busy street. View of building facade, "Continental Palace." More people, bicycles, cars and motorcycles. Lighting much darker. People getting out of car. So dark, you can barely tell what this is. White man and woman walking toward camera, then they greet camera operator. More people, bikes, cars and motorcycles in street. People walking down street.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL AND FINANCIAL MATERIAL (1932-1994, n.d.), 3 linear feet
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This series consists of general materials about Birkby's life, finances, and education. Included are such materials as clippings, curriculum vitae, legal papers, class notes and drawings, portfolio materials, scrapbooks, and sketchbooks.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE (1955-1994, n.d.), 1 linear ft.
  This series consists primarily of incoming correspondence. The few surviving drafts of outgoing letters are interfiled with the incoming by the name of the correspondent. The series is arranged in two subseries: Individuals, containing letters or cards from major correspondents (3 or more letters) filed alphabetically; and General, filed chronologically. Undated general correspondence is filed alphabetically at the end of the subseries.
- SERIES III. ARCHITECTURE (1962-1993, n.d.), 9 linear ft.